<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aly Raffauf</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Aly Raffauf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fixing AMD &amp; Intel Power Management under Linux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-30-pp_to_epp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2024-01-30-pp_to_epp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/imgs/pp-to-epp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;pp_to_epp.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently in the market for a laptop, and got a great deal on an Asus ROG Zephyrus G14 from Best Buy. It&amp;rsquo;s a powerful machine, with an AMD Ryzen 7840HS processor, 16GB RAM, and an Nvidia RTX 4060, and, at first, seemed to work well enough under Linux, my preferred operating system. In the month-ish that I owned it, I discovered a wonderful community of folks actively working on developing and supporting &lt;a href=&#34;https://asus-linux.org/&#34;&gt;Linux on Asus laptops&lt;/a&gt;, filling in the userspace gaps and patching the kernel as needed to deliver a somewhat workable experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/imgs/pp-to-epp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;pp_to_epp.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently in the market for a laptop, and got a great deal on an Asus ROG Zephyrus G14 from Best Buy. It&amp;rsquo;s a powerful machine, with an AMD Ryzen 7840HS processor, 16GB RAM, and an Nvidia RTX 4060, and, at first, seemed to work well enough under Linux, my preferred operating system. In the month-ish that I owned it, I discovered a wonderful community of folks actively working on developing and supporting &lt;a href=&#34;https://asus-linux.org/&#34;&gt;Linux on Asus laptops&lt;/a&gt;, filling in the userspace gaps and patching the kernel as needed to deliver a somewhat workable experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After weeks of diving through forums, the asus-linux discord, and random bug trackers, I found one of the biggest issues on modern AMD laptops involves the &lt;code&gt;amd-pstate&lt;/code&gt; driver&amp;rsquo;s exposure of the processor&amp;rsquo;s energy performance preference. EPP works like a far more intelligent and impactful version of old school CPU governors. The &lt;code&gt;amd-pstate&lt;/code&gt; kernel driver &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.kernel.org/admin-guide/pm/amd-pstate.html&#34;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt; explain this further, but the gist is EPP is the key to getting the most performance &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the best battery life out of your laptop CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the version of &lt;code&gt;power-profiles-daemon&lt;/code&gt; currently being shipped by most distros doesn&amp;rsquo;t automatically adjust the EPP based on the user&amp;rsquo;s stated performance profile, leading to increased battery usage, particularly at idle or when doing simple tasks. Power-profiles-daemon is unable to use the &lt;code&gt;amd-pstate&lt;/code&gt; driver, so the setting never gets adjusted, leading to mismatched performance and cooling choices between &lt;code&gt;platform_profile&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;amd-pstate&lt;/code&gt; on modern AMD laptops. Luckily, the community—particularly Marcin &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/marcinx64&#34;&gt;@marcinx64&lt;/a&gt;—have developed a simple Python &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/marcinx64&#34;&gt;daemon&lt;/a&gt; to automatically adjust the EPP based on the chosen power profile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, after a series of hardware problems (severe IPS backlight bleed), an exchange, and standard Nvidia buggyness (at least on Linux) later, I ended up returning the Asus for a Lenovo Yoga 9i with an Intel Core i7 1360P, 16GB RAM, and integrated graphics. I know, totally different product category. Oh well. But as it turns out, the &lt;code&gt;intel-pstate&lt;/code&gt; driver is also affected by the same issue in &lt;code&gt;power-profiles-daemon&lt;/code&gt;, but no utility exists for Intel users. Luckily, the interfaces exposed by the kernel for controlling EPP are basically the same, so I&amp;rsquo;ve forked Marcin&amp;rsquo;s utility to provide a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/alychace/pp-to-epp&#34;&gt;temporary solution&lt;/a&gt; for Intel and AMD users alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an open &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/upower/power-profiles-daemon/-/issues/107&#34;&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;code&gt;power-profiles-daemon&lt;/code&gt; to allow it to leverage both &lt;code&gt;platform_profile&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;amd-pstate&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;intel-pstate&lt;/code&gt; simultaneously to deliver the best performance or power savings possible. Until then, this daemon provides a solid workaround for pstate power control for GNU/Linux users. For my G14, and now my Yoga 9i, this means getting battery life in Fedora 39 that meets or exceeds Windows 11. It should also work under other distros that use systemd (sorry protest distros!) and power-profiles-daemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I know this is a big departure from this blog&amp;rsquo;s previous content. A lot has happened since then: a phd program left behind, a worldwide pandemic, a total career change, and several years of wandering. This blog has always been about technology in some form or fashion, so why the hell not? Beats making a new one.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xenofeminism: Immanence or Transcendence?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-06-14-xf_immanence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-06-14-xf_immanence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Introduced in 2015’s &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism: A Politics for Alienation&lt;/em&gt;, a production of the &lt;em&gt;Laboria Cuboniks&lt;/em&gt; collective of academics, artists, and writers from around the globe, Xenofeminism (XF) presents “a technomaterialist, anti-naturalist, and gender abolitionist form of feminism” (Hester 2018, 6), which avows the technological, disavows the natural, and searches for a way out of the perennial hangups of contemporary feminist, not just through a re-hash of cyberfeminist/Harawayan language but as a project that intimately practices what it preaches—&lt;em&gt;Laboria&lt;/em&gt; herself is already an exercise in high-intensity cybernetics, both a singular entity and multiplicitous collective: autonomous nodes working neither in homogenous unity nor in heat-death isolationist heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Introduced in 2015’s &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism: A Politics for Alienation&lt;/em&gt;, a production of the &lt;em&gt;Laboria Cuboniks&lt;/em&gt; collective of academics, artists, and writers from around the globe, Xenofeminism (XF) presents “a technomaterialist, anti-naturalist, and gender abolitionist form of feminism” (Hester 2018, 6), which avows the technological, disavows the natural, and searches for a way out of the perennial hangups of contemporary feminist, not just through a re-hash of cyberfeminist/Harawayan language but as a project that intimately practices what it preaches—&lt;em&gt;Laboria&lt;/em&gt; herself is already an exercise in high-intensity cybernetics, both a singular entity and multiplicitous collective: autonomous nodes working neither in homogenous unity nor in heat-death isolationist heterogeneity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an anagram of the “Nicolas Bourbaki” group of twentieth century French mathematicians, Cuboniks also advances an affirmation of abstraction as an epistopolitical necessity for twenty-first century claims on equality. Espousing reason and vigorous anti-naturalism, she seeks to dismantle gender implicitly. Cuboniks is a multi-taloned, tetra-headed creature uncomfortably navigating the fields of art, design, architecture, archeology, philosophy, techno-feminism, sexuality studies, digital music, translation, writing and regular experiments with the use of evolutionary algorithms in offensive cybersecurity (qtd. in Holt 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through Laboria, the collective (Helen Hester, Lucca Fraser, Amy Ireland, Diann Bauer, Katrina Burch and Patricia Reed) speaks as one: indeed, the magic of this collective exercise of writing is that she manages to say many things (some quite contradictory, as we shall see) in but one seemingly cohesive voice. XFM recalls, in style, form, and rhetoric, two previous techno-feminist manifestos—1991’s &lt;em&gt;Cyberfeminist Manifesto&lt;/em&gt; from Australia’s VNS Matrix collective and Donna Haraway’s &lt;em&gt;A Manifesto for Cyborgs&lt;/em&gt;—as well as 1971’s _ The Dialectic of Sex_ by Shulamith Firestone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manifesto itself plays host to a hodgepodge of technofuturist and cyberfeminist ideas—a massive polemic data-dump on a wide range of contemporary feminist dogma, ranging from new iterations of gender essentialism to Feminism’s suspicious and even naturalist outlook on techno-economic change (including posthuman forms of technology and reproduction). For XF, there is no room for ‘suspicion’ or renewed calls to the ‘natural’ or the fixed: “Nothing should be accepted as fixed, permanent, or ‘given’—neither material conditions nor social forms….Anyone who’s been deemed ‘unnatural’ in the face of reigning biological norms, anyone who’s experienced injustices wrought in the name of natural order, will realize that the glorification of ‘nature’ has nothing to offer us—the queer and trans among us, the differently-abled, as well as those who have suffered discrimination due to pregnancy or duties connected to child-rearing” (Cuboniks 2015, 1). XF is thus explicitly gender abolitionist, race abolitionist, class abolitionist, and “vehemently anti-naturalist”. For XF, “Essentialist naturalism reeks of theology—the sooner it is exorcised, the better” (Cuboniks 2015, 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been many attempts to tease out what &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; Xenofeminism is—theorists have taken microscopic laser cutters to the manifesto to neatly derive &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; meaning and &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; vector in its theorizing. Since publication in 2015, there have been a flurry of articles critiquing, reassembling, and tweaking many of the core affirmations of the manifesto (as, perhaps, was intended!). But in this it has also become popular to compare and contrast each of Laboria’s component authors and to speculate on their influence and/or “breaks” with the dispersive and contradictory affirmations laid out in the manifesto—the assumption being that there &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be as many possible Xenofeminisms (of varying moral and political quality) as there are authors. Following the manifesto’s publication in 2015, Helen Hester, one of six assemblages pulling themselves together from Laboria’s scraps, went on to publish a full length book, also under the &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism&lt;/em&gt; name. Despite its broad name, &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism&lt;/em&gt; focuses mostly on but one issue raised in the collective’s manifesto: reproductive rights and technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether or not Hester “breaks” from the original manifesto, there has at very least been the &lt;em&gt;perception&lt;/em&gt; of such a break, which has lead some to differentiate her work from Laboria’s collective production. For example, Sophie Lewis, author of &lt;em&gt;Full Surrogacy Now: Feminism Against Family&lt;/em&gt;, has explicitly held up Hester over the other members of Laboria Cuboniks—dismissing poet Amy Ireland’s statements as merely “esoteric, ecstatic and/or nihilist-apolitical” (Lewis 2019), and linking some parts of XF—especially those espoused in the manifesto—to a so-called “dark lineage” of philosophy’s unpopular kids—specifically British philosopher Nick Land (others, such as Jules Joanne Gleeson&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, have further linked the manifesto to Martin Heidegger, and thus to a lineage of esoteric fascism). Yet in elevating it over the others, Lewis, at least, finds promise in Hester’s “‘version of XF’ [that] already vindicates reproductive justice, democratic practices of scientific bricolage and irreverent collective biohacking” (Lewis 2019). It is Hester’s work that I’ll focus on here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Briefly, and to clarify, it is not my intention to trace XF’s “dark lineage”, or to rehabilitate said kinship (always figured patrilineally and arborescently) in the face of criticism—I don’t have the time or interest to do either, and it seems irrelevant to the more critical issue Lewis’s thought inspires: what could it mean to have a ‘version of XF’, and does Helen Hester actually have one? Is Xenofeminism a cohesive ideology in the first place, one that can be easily broken away from? How and why is Hester’s work held in such esteem, over the others? After all, XF—following through on Haraway’s influence—never makes any claims to innocence. XF is also not, as the manifesto is quick to point out, a recipe, “or a single-purpose tool by which a determinate problem is solved” (XF p. 10). Xenofeminism is not a political program but “a platform, an incipient ambition to construct a new language for sexual politics—a language that seizes its own methods as materials to be reworked, and incrementally bootstraps itself into existence” (Cubonics 2015, 10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, here I am primarily interested in the epistemic and ontological foundations behind the manifesto’s most provocative call and sign off—“If nature is unjust, change nature!”. What is nature, and how is the concept criticized—and employed—in Xenofeminism and subsequent criticism? And, most importantly, if Xenofeminism is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a political program, then what kind of politics does it produce? Does subsequent work—particularly Helen Hester’s—“break” with the manifesto, or are there deeper contradictions and tensions that have yet to be addressed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, nature does a lot of work for XF—and XF works through it, on it, and over it. For example, the manifesto laments the “sense of the world’s volatility and artificiality [that] seems to have faded from contemporary queer and feminist politics, in favour of a plural but static constellation of gender identities, in whose bleak light equations of the good and the natural are stubbornly restored” (Cuboniks 2015, 4-5). For XF, calls to nature are power moves—linguistic expressions of the will to power that inadvertently locks one into a prison—in which we “are told to seek solace in unfreedom, staking claims on being ‘born’ this way, as if offering an excuse with nature’s blessing” (Cuboniks 2015, 5). Appeals to nature—or more specifically, truth in nature—are “a retreat from what makes trans and queer politics more than just a lobby: that it is an arduous assertion of freedom against an order that seemed immutable” (Cuboniks 2015, 5). Here, nature is figured as a kind of limit which must be overcome—an order that can be overthrown or escape. This xenofeminism confronts a prison, sure, but prisons have outsides: they are escapable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet while this XF is embedded rather neatly in the language of transcendence, hardly two pages later the manifesto shatters any illusion of transcendence or the possibility (possibilities?) therein. With a heavy dose of Donne Haraway, XFM reads: “‘Nature’—understood here, as the unbounded arena of science—is all there is“ (Cuboniks 2015, 4). Where the previous XF almost yearns for a kind of innocence (though I’m sure no one will ever admit to it), this other Xenofeminism—where nature is not a limit but “all there is”—invokes Haraway’s unwavering refusal to tease out the organic and the inorganic: “we are all chimeras, theorized and fabricated hybrids of machine and organism” (Cuboniks 2015, 2). In this respect, XF seems to undermine itself. From &lt;em&gt;A Cyborg Manifesto&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is certainly true that postmodernist strategies, like my cyborg myth, subvert myriad organic wholes (for example, the poem, the primitive culture, the biological organism). In short, the certainty of what counts as nature — a source of insight and promise of innocence — is undermined, probably fatally. The transcendent authorization of interpretation is lost, and with it the ontology grounding &amp;lsquo;Western&amp;rsquo; epistemology. But the alternative is not cynicism or faithlessness, that is, some version of abstract existence, like the accounts of technological determinism destroying &amp;lsquo;man&amp;rsquo; by the &amp;lsquo;machine&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;meaningful political action&amp;rsquo; by the &amp;rsquo;text&amp;rsquo;. Who cyborgs will be is a radical question; the answers are a matter of survival (Haraway 2005, 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a certain Harawayan disavowal in the manifesto’s affirmation of alienation—“We are all alienated – but have we ever been otherwise?”—not in alienation per se but in XF’s acceptance of the immanent conditions as they are, as seen in its seizure of “alienation as impetus to generate new worlds” (Cuboniks 2015, 1). This snippet—or slice or ‘version’—of XF presents, following Haraway, not the issue of  &lt;em&gt;becoming&lt;/em&gt;, but a factual observation that we &lt;em&gt;already are&lt;/em&gt;, and perhaps always have been, cyborg creatures. For Haraway, this precludes the appropriation of nature/culture by the other:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cyborg is resolutely committed to partiality, irony, intimacy, and perversity. It is oppositional, utopian, and completely without innocence. No longer structured by the polarity of public and private, the cyborg defines a technological polls based partly on a revolution of social relations in the oikos, the household. Nature and culture are reworked; the one can no longer be the resource for appropriation or incorporation by the other (Haraway 2006, 2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But any staunch endorsement of Haraway’s paradigm is difficult to support, and ‘nature’ only gets more bizarre. Elsewhere, XF &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; seek the appropriation of nature by culture—it sees nature as, at the very least, a malleable object that can be labored over and, once again breaking with Haraway, &lt;em&gt;appropriated&lt;/em&gt;. How else could the manifesto’s signature sign off—“If nature is unjust, change nature!”—be possible? If nature is not a discreet object, how does one “change it”? Instead, for this XF, nature is to be controlled, surpassed, manipulated—it is no longer a “refuge of injustice”, but something to be put to new forms of political utility: abolish gender, yes, but “[l]et a hundred sexes bloom” (Cuboniks 2015, 6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Laboria is therefore juggling two seemingly contradictory affirmations—the political call to &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; cyborgs (to transcend nature) and the immanent philosophical (but not apolitical!) fact that we &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; cyborgs. Tentatively, I call these the Haraway position on one hand—that we are already cyborgs and must find solace within this fact—and the Firestonian position on the other—that we must (or will) become cyborgs to surpass the conditions of the current order, transcending towards a gender abolitionist horizon. For Haraway, this means (roughly) &lt;em&gt;a politics of a cope&lt;/em&gt;—learning to “survive” the immanent (and thus already present) conditions of postmodernity. There is no “escape”—no prior authenticity to uncover, no new authenticity to construct. Meanwhile for Firestone, “we are no longer just animals…humanity has begun to transcend Nature: we can no longer justify the maintenance of a discriminatory sex class system on grounds of its origins in nature” (Firestone 2003). Rather than waxing poetic about a lost authenticity or nature (in the vein of Mary Daly and other ‘goddess’ feminists), Firestone yearn for a new world—a different world—over the horizon. While both are committed to XF’s staunch anti-naturalism—and gender abolitionism—the conditions that facilitate their dynamic conceptions of nature are quite different, and have very different risks. These are very different cyborg politics!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firestone’s position—espoused in &lt;em&gt;The Dialectic of Sex&lt;/em&gt;—accepts Freud’s account of woman’s “disadvantage” (i.e. her reproductive role, her size, her lack of penis) as a given, arguing for a promethean overcoming of sexual difference vis-a-vis technological innovation (and, importantly, &lt;em&gt;progress&lt;/em&gt;). This is what Hester’s post-manifesto work, &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism&lt;/em&gt;, dedicates itself to—the role of DIY reproductive tools (such as the Del-Em and artificial wombs) in a liberationist politics of gender abolition. Hester summarizes her (and Firestone’s) position here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Nina Power notes, ‘Firestone’s approach to the question of sex is refreshingly blunt. Sex difference is real. Men and women exist, and possess asymmetrical physical capacities which have historically made existence for women extremely difficult and frequently unpleasant or even lethal.’ Firestone observes, however, that with the development of increasingly sophisticated means of birth control and artificial reproduction, technology has ‘created real pre-conditions for overthrowing these oppressive “natural” conditions, along with their cultural reinforcements’. For a condition to be described as natural at this historical juncture is no reason to assume that it cannot be changed (Hester 2018, 23).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet Hester has to do quite a lot of work to retrofit for new political (or, and I think this is more accurate, &lt;em&gt;linguistic&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ontological&lt;/em&gt; conditions). Whereas “&lt;em&gt;The Dialectic of Sex&lt;/em&gt; insists that the sex-class system is based on disadvantages suffered by those capable of conceiving, restating, and bearing a child…[and] this group is called women”, Hester suggests that we “may not wish to follow her in this”, instead preferring a plurality of “embodied differences” (which nonetheless seems to privilege the “gestating” component of these differences). Hester distinguishes between, for example, certain trends in trans politics which see nature as “both a stable origin and incontestable endpoint—a view that is obviously at odds with xenofeminist ideas”, which (in her account) would trend toward a view of nature as a “protean platform”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no matter how flexible—or ‘protean’—this platform, Hester cannot—and does not seem to want to—escape this Firestonian notion of transcendence. Moreover, this dissonance seems unnoticed and certainly unresolved. In her book, Hester describes Laboria Cuboniks as “Haraway’s disobedient daughters” (Hester 2018). But this is quite a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of disobedience—a different paradigm entirely! Hester writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We too find ‘discourses of natural harmony, the nonalien, and purity unsalvageable for understanding our genealogy in the New World Order, Inc.’, and agree that it ‘will not help – intellectually, morally, or politically – to appeal to the natural and the pure’. (Hester 2018, 20).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all well and good—but for a feminism that claims a direct lineage (albeit disobedient), this is a very slim point of commonality in a sea of difference. What does Xenofeminism even think it is here? Hester—and perhaps other Xenofeminists—seem convinced of a Harawayan legacy that is directly contradicted through their transcendent politics. And if there is a “break” in Hester’s text from the collective manifesto, it is certainly not expressed here. And because these contradictions were already present within the manifesto, it would seem impossible to chart a clear trajectory for any one member—unless we are going to go down the fruitless forensic paranoia of reconstructing who wrote each individual line and selected each word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems, then, that there are not as many Xenofeminisms as there are Xenofeminists—there are &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;! This certainly supports the various viral metaphors which permeate XF—the coexistence of distinct strains of diverse origins within the same bodies/texts. What, then, is the role of Haraway’s spectral presence on an emerging Xenofeminism canon? There is a very real contradiction between the Harawayan lineage that is accepted or affirmed seemingly by default, and the reality of the texts (both the manifesto and Hester’s book) as a polyvalent and contradictory assemblage that leans heavily, especially in Hester’s work, towards Firestone and transcendent theories of the natural.  This makes it all the more confusing that some, like Sophie Lewis, have used Haraway as a yardstick by which to judge Xenofeminism. Lewis acknowledges parallels with Haraway’s work—“whose incantatory language [XF] is rebooting for the 21st century”, but claims that XF oversimplifies Haraway’s “anti-colonial, non-duallist queer materialism” (Lewis 2019). Lewis specifically calls the “concept of ‘alienation’ touted in the XFM&amp;hellip;a misunderstanding of the pro-human&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; post-humanism of the Cyborg Manifesto”, praising Hester for having “happily” abandoned it in her book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But does this actually mean Hester is somehow closer to Haraway’s vision? Is she less “disobedient”, or does she compare more favorably against who is now employed more as a (don’t call it father) figure over the whole ordeal? This seems unlikely—in fact, if Hester “breaks” with the manifesto, it is only to become &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; Harawayan—to embrace a transcendent theory of nature and to further embrace what is, underneath the fresh coat of paint of language like “gestators” and “menstruators”, fundamentally a dualist, albeit perhaps queer, materialist program that hardly differs at all from Firestone’s 1971 polemic. How does a recognition—following Hester—of “embodied differences” change the fact that we are ultimately talking about a dialectic notion of history wherein there are gestators and non-gestators? This is hardly conceptually distinct from the “men and women” of Firestone’s work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s one thing to acknowledge Haraway’s contribution (even through disagreement), but it is altogether more problematic to ignore the dissonance in one’s own work that prevents any realization of the kind of politics Haraway hoped for (whether she continues to hope for those politics, I can’t say). The result is that Hester’s work (and I think you see this in Lewis’s work too, though that is beyond the scope of this paper) suffers from nearly identical problems as Firestone’s radical polemics: dualisms, progress narratives, and an awkward mismatched recognition of, particularly, queer/trans bodies that seemed sprinkled on at the last minute. While this is also beyond the scope of this engagement, I do wonder: what would it look like to strip Firestone down to parts—to embed her as a set of strategies within a Harawayan paradigm? Certainly this is not the kind of project Laboria’s critics have offered—but I think I’m right in finding it much in the intended spirit of &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism: A Politics of Alienation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuboniks, Laboria. 2015. “Xenofeminism: A Politics for Alienation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firestone, Shulamith. 2003. &lt;em&gt;The Dialectic of Sex: The Case for Feminist Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. 1. ed. New York, NY: Farrar, Straus and Giroux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haraway, Donna. 2006. “A Cyborg Manifesto: Science, Technology, and Socialist-Feminism in the Late Twentieth Century.” In &lt;em&gt;The Transgender Studies Reader&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Susan Stryker and Stephen Whittle. Routledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hester, Helen. 2018. &lt;em&gt;Xenofeminism&lt;/em&gt;. Theory Redux. Cambridge, UK ; Medford, MA: Polity Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holt, Macon. 2018. “What Is Xenofeminism?” &lt;em&gt;Ark Review&lt;/em&gt;, February 13, 2018. &lt;a href=&#34;http://arkbooks.dk/what-is-xenofeminism/&#34;&gt;http://arkbooks.dk/what-is-xenofeminism/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lewis, Sophie. 2019. “Cyborg Sentiments.” &lt;em&gt;Red Pepper&lt;/em&gt;, March 7, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redpepper.org.uk/cyborg-sentiments/&#34;&gt;https://www.redpepper.org.uk/cyborg-sentiments/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gleeson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.metamute.org/editorial/articles/breakthroughs-bait-xenofeminism-alienation&#34;&gt;dispute&lt;/a&gt; seems to be on the Marxist vs. Heideggerian concept of alienation and its deployment in XFM. I don&amp;rsquo;t care enough to comment.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given some of Haraway&amp;rsquo;s recent interests&amp;ndash;including her &lt;a href=&#34;https://logicmag.io/nature/a-giant-bumptious-litter/&#34;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; on Xenofeminism&amp;ndash;we might rethink how &amp;lsquo;pro-human&amp;rsquo; her politics turned out to be.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irigaray, Desirability, and Materialist (trans)Feminism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-20-irigaray_desirability_matfem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-20-irigaray_desirability_matfem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps in no small part to those all-too-eager to drop the word “material” as shorthand for “biological” or “true”, materialist feminism has of late become associated with various forms of so-called “exclusionary” feminisms—TERFs, SWERFs, and all the rest. But (and this is quite ironic) this strikes me—given the history of materialist feminism—a rather idealist appropriation of the term. I am not interested in who is “really” a woman, but in one’s economic situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;politics of desirability&lt;/em&gt; is a concept with a lot of currency in today’s feminism&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, especially in accounts of bias in sexual preference. It’s also been endlessly and ruthlessly critiqued, largely on account of those who would police and moralize on individual desire and preference. Indeed, this drive to moralize is precisely what I intend to avoid here—it is not individual moral failing (nor is it reducible to “ideology”), but rather it is material relations which give rise to politics of desirability cross-cut by class, gender, race, size, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Women on the Market&lt;/em&gt;, Luce Irigaray re-reads Claude Levi-Strauss’s old observation—that women are commodities exchanged among men—through Marx’s account of the commodity form laid out in &lt;em&gt;Capital, Vol. 1&lt;/em&gt;. While many Marxist-Feminists readings of Marx have sought simply to re-read the proletarian as “woman, too”, and radical feminists claim “woman, instead”, Irigaray realizes woman as not simply a proletarian economic subject but as a commodity produced through abstract human (read: male) labour.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;Two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Perhaps in no small part to those all-too-eager to drop the word “material” as shorthand for “biological” or “true”, materialist feminism has of late become associated with various forms of so-called “exclusionary” feminisms—TERFs, SWERFs, and all the rest. But (and this is quite ironic) this strikes me—given the history of materialist feminism—a rather idealist appropriation of the term. I am not interested in who is “really” a woman, but in one’s economic situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;politics of desirability&lt;/em&gt; is a concept with a lot of currency in today’s feminism&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, especially in accounts of bias in sexual preference. It’s also been endlessly and ruthlessly critiqued, largely on account of those who would police and moralize on individual desire and preference. Indeed, this drive to moralize is precisely what I intend to avoid here—it is not individual moral failing (nor is it reducible to “ideology”), but rather it is material relations which give rise to politics of desirability cross-cut by class, gender, race, size, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Women on the Market&lt;/em&gt;, Luce Irigaray re-reads Claude Levi-Strauss’s old observation—that women are commodities exchanged among men—through Marx’s account of the commodity form laid out in &lt;em&gt;Capital, Vol. 1&lt;/em&gt;. While many Marxist-Feminists readings of Marx have sought simply to re-read the proletarian as “woman, too”, and radical feminists claim “woman, instead”, Irigaray realizes woman as not simply a proletarian economic subject but as a commodity produced through abstract human (read: male) labour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all the systems of exchange that organize patriarchal societies and all the modalities of productive work that are recognized, valued, and rewarded in these societies are men&amp;rsquo;s business. The production of women, signs, and commodities is always referred back to men (when a man buys a girl, he &amp;quot; pays&amp;quot; the father or the brother, not the mother . . . ),  and they always pass from one man to another, from one group of men to another. The work force is thus always assumed to be masculine, and &amp;quot; products&amp;quot; are objects to be used, objects of transaction among men alone (Irigaray, p. 171)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irigaray reframes capitalism as a series of “hom(m)o-sexual” exchanges and marketized social arrangements. The pun here is perhaps more obvious in French—Irigaray combines &lt;em&gt;homme&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;homo&lt;/em&gt; to stress the fundamentally homosexual (read: &lt;em&gt;homosocial&lt;/em&gt;) nature of these libidinally-charged phallo-economic exchanges. Either way, men serve as the primary agent of exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we say &lt;em&gt;women are commodities&lt;/em&gt;, I think there is a real danger in a totalizing and homogenizing account in which differences between women are erased or unresolved. Certainly, this is the usual suspicion to which one is quite accustomed to applying to any account of sexual oppression or discrimination. And surely, it is not without some cause for concern: mainstream gender critical feminism trips over its own ‘materialist’ claims to a ‘sex-based’ account, erasing difference in service of some totally-not-idealist conception of womanhood predicated on an unqualified and totalizing worship of a homogenous female-defining biological difference. But this is far from Irigaray’s project. Irigaray hints at these differences in her account of &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; as it differs among women, starting with three of women’s most ubiquitous roles: mother, virgin, prostitute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To backtrack briefly to &lt;em&gt;Capital&lt;/em&gt;, recall that Marx distinguishes between a commodity’s use-value and its exchange value. For Marx, “[t]he usefulness of a thing makes it a use-value”, and its usefulness is “conditioned by the physical properties of the commodity, and has no existence apart from the latter…it is therefore the physical body of the commodity itself” (Marx, p. 152). Meanwhile, “[e]xchange value appears first of all as the quantitative relation, the proportion, in which use-values of one kind exchange for use-values of another kind” (Marx, p. 154). For Irigaray, women, as any other commodity, “…are thus two things at once: utilitarian objects and bearers of value” (Irigaray, p. 175). As Irigaray explains, “just as nature has to be subjected to man in order to be­ come a commodity, so, it appears, does &amp;ldquo;the development of a normal woman.&amp;quot;” (187). The natural “properties of a woman’s body have to be suppressed and subordinated to the exigencies of its transformation into an object of circulation among men”. Her “natural utility is overridden by the exchange function” (Irigaray, p. 187).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not have time to rehash Irigaray’s (multiple) vivid arguments—they remain excellently stated and reasonably accessible. For now it suffices to say that variances in women’s use-value and exchange value are central to Irigaray’s tripartite role distinction, which is far more relevant in the scope of our business here. For Irigaray, “[a]s mother, woman remains on the side of (re)productive nature”, and because the incest taboo prohibits “productive nature to enter in exchanges among men”, mothers, whom Irigaray refers to as “reproductive instruments marked with the name of the father and enclosed in his house…must be private proper­ty, excluded from exchange” (Irigaray p. 185). The virginal woman, meanwhile, “is pure exchange value” (Irigaray, p. 186). Virgins are “nothing but the possibility, the plane, the sign of relations among men…envelope[s] veiling what is really at stake in social exchange” (Irigaray, p. 186). The passage from virgin to mother “is accompanied by the violation of an envelope: the hymen, which has taken on the value of taboo, the taboo of virginity”, and once “deflowered” she is “relegated to the status of use value…to her entrapment in private property; she is removed from exchange among men” (Irigaray, p. 186).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This notion of &lt;em&gt;desirability&lt;/em&gt; employed in the liberal feminist blogosphere grafts quite cleanly onto exchange value, though their analyses seldom go beyond petty moralism. This grafting of these two concepts certainly makes a lot of sense for a subset of women to which Irigaray referred—in this case, cisgender and white women—who are guided into womanhood by their fathers, exchanged to their husbands, and ultimately used (as use-value) for sexual release, home-making, status-signaling, and, most notably, for the ho(m)mo-sexual reproduction of the species in the marriage contract&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. But what about those women who have been excluded from the marriage contract altogether? For brevity, I’ll speak here specifically about trans women, although this is certainly pertinent to other women as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is with trans women—treated across society as &lt;em&gt;undesirable&lt;/em&gt; or otherwise inappropriate romantic and sexual objects—that we find an important contradiction. Despite the endless telegraphing of their undesirability and the punishment of them and those who choose them as partners, they comprise nonetheless one of the most desirable categories—commodities—in portnography and prostitution. to explain this? Surely this points to fetishization—language which is now more colloquial than specific—but how exactly does that work? Irigaray’s account of the prostitute points us in the right direction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prostitute remains to be considered. Explicitly condemned by the social order, she is implicitly tolerated. No doubt because the break between usage and exchange her case, clear­ cut? In her case, the qualities of woman&amp;rsquo;s body are &amp;ldquo;useful.&amp;rdquo; However, these qualities have &amp;ldquo;value&amp;rdquo; only because they have already been appropriated by a man, and because they serve as the locus of relations—hidden ones—between men. Prostitution amounts to &lt;em&gt;usage that is exchanged&lt;/em&gt;. Usage that is not merely potential: it has already been realized. The woman&amp;rsquo;s body is valuable because it has already been used. In the extreme case, the more it has served, the more it is worth. Not because its natural assets have been put to use this way, but, on the contrary, because its nature has been &amp;ldquo;used up,&amp;rdquo; and has become once again no more than a vehicle for relations among men (Irigaray, p. 186)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cisgender white women’s use-value (or potential thereof) pertains to their role as “productive nature” in domestic sphere (reproduction, domesticity, etc.) and their products’ role as “legal tender” in the social order (Irigaray, p. 185). For trans women, who lack the capacity to reproduce the species (&lt;em&gt;to reproduce the same&lt;/em&gt;), there is no taboo (the incest taboo) confining them to the home—in fact, quite the opposite is true: they are disowned by the father and (all-too-often) jettisoned from the home. There is no pathway to marriage—no solidification of men’s relationships through the marriage contract—available to trans women, precisely because of this variance in use value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while gender critical feminists take this lack of confinement—and especially this biological difference—as somehow proof that trans women somehow escape patriarchal exploitation, this could not be further from the truth. It is not women’s role in the domestic sphere that defined her—it is her appropriation and exchange by man in these hidden social relations between men, and men alone. Trans women, both like and, especially given rates of prostitution and sex trafficking, &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; sex workers, are already appropriated by men among whom they exchange/are exchanged. Whereas much of the sexual excitement of the virgin centers around her &lt;em&gt;potential yet unrealized&lt;/em&gt; use, trans women are deprived of any innocence such a virginal status might confer. The qualities of her body—here almost exclusively her sexual organs and their vitality—constitute Irigaray’s &lt;em&gt;usage that is exchanged&lt;/em&gt;. Body modification serves to use up whatever that was previously available—she becomes a mirrored reflection of the male buyer. Unlike the virgin, and especially unlike the mother, the more men she has served, the more valuable her (in actuality, &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt;) product becomes. She is exchanged freely and without restrictive taboo. Like Patricia Hill-Collins&amp;rsquo; notion of black women as both “insiders” and “outsiders” (Collins 1968), trans women find themselves nominally disavowed and condemned while nonetheless implicitly, and quite materially, factored into the (economic) equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, gender critical feminists are unlikely to be moved by these (quite incomplete, maybe even problematic) arguments, but I hope what I have tried to present here invites more feminist discussion that a) is &lt;em&gt;meaningfully&lt;/em&gt; inclusive of non-cis and non-white women and b) does not achieve this inclusion through meaningless idealist platitudes and empty and unsupported assertions that ‘trans women are women’ that, far too often, go unelaborated in ostensibly queer/trans/feminist accounts of gender/sex. Surely, there are no innocent parties in this ordeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collins, Patricia Hill. 1986. “Learning from the Outsider Within: The Sociological Significance of Black Feminist Thought.” Social Problems 33 (6): S14–32. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2307/800672&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/800672&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irigaray, Luce. 1985. This Sex Which Is Not One. Ithaca, N.Y: Cornell University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx, Karl, Ben Fowkes, and David Fernbach. 1981. Capital: A Critique of Political Economy. V. 1: Penguin Classics. London ; New York, N.Y: Penguin Books in association with New Left Review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the worst offenders: &lt;a href=&#34;https://everydayfeminism.com/2016/04/attraction-desire-political/&#34;&gt;https://everydayfeminism.com/2016/04/attraction-desire-political/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without doubt, important changes to this basic paradigm have proliferated Western culture over the past 70 years. However, a properly material analysis ought to take still-recent history into account. I would also wager that this simple structure has not changed as drastically as some would suggest.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sadie Plant&#39;s Weaving Methodology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-17-plant_weaving_method/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-02-17-plant_weaving_method/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What follows is a series of footnotes on Sadie Plant’s &lt;em&gt;The Future Looms: Weaving Women and Cybernetics&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;putting into practice her account of the relationship between weaving, footnotes, and knowledge production. This is nothing definitive (nor should it be), just a series of notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes are ordered by their appearance in the text and their page number. 0-45 = footnote 0, page 45.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0-45&lt;/strong&gt;. Plant takes that task already apparent in the subtitle&amp;ndash;weaving&amp;ndash;as a serious feminist methodological practice. Weaving is a cartography: Plant maps the history of women’s near-ubiquitous role in weaving itself from pre-industrial anthropological accounts, through the invention of the Jacquard Loom, onto the invention of the earliest computer systems, but there is only a scrambled sense of progression. This &amp;ldquo;map&amp;rdquo; is to be distinguished from what Deleuze-Guattari call a &amp;ldquo;tracing&amp;rdquo;, i.e. it is not in service of a single generative line (or an authoritative account) of historical events, but rather as a series of interwoven and rewoven positions. For Plant, like Deleuze-Guattari, &amp;ldquo;…any point of a rhizome can be connected to any other, and must be&amp;rdquo; (Deleuze-Guattari, A Thousand Plateaus, p. 7).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;What follows is a series of footnotes on Sadie Plant’s &lt;em&gt;The Future Looms: Weaving Women and Cybernetics&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash;putting into practice her account of the relationship between weaving, footnotes, and knowledge production. This is nothing definitive (nor should it be), just a series of notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnotes are ordered by their appearance in the text and their page number. 0-45 = footnote 0, page 45.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;0-45&lt;/strong&gt;. Plant takes that task already apparent in the subtitle&amp;ndash;weaving&amp;ndash;as a serious feminist methodological practice. Weaving is a cartography: Plant maps the history of women’s near-ubiquitous role in weaving itself from pre-industrial anthropological accounts, through the invention of the Jacquard Loom, onto the invention of the earliest computer systems, but there is only a scrambled sense of progression. This &amp;ldquo;map&amp;rdquo; is to be distinguished from what Deleuze-Guattari call a &amp;ldquo;tracing&amp;rdquo;, i.e. it is not in service of a single generative line (or an authoritative account) of historical events, but rather as a series of interwoven and rewoven positions. For Plant, like Deleuze-Guattari, &amp;ldquo;…any point of a rhizome can be connected to any other, and must be&amp;rdquo; (Deleuze-Guattari, A Thousand Plateaus, p. 7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1-45&lt;/strong&gt;. The decision to open with an ostensibly fictional account of Ada Lovelace’s life&amp;ndash;by cyberpunk authors William Gibson and Bruce Sterling&amp;ndash;points to Plant’s general ambivalence towards any harsh distinction between fact and fiction. The point here is not to claim any authority to a capital-T Truth, but rather to a ‘partial’ account that hedges any claim to completion. Haraway’s &amp;ldquo;god trick&amp;rdquo; is nowhere to be found. Plant treats Lovelace’s diaries not as an eye-witness account but as cultural artifacts that can be harvested from and woven together with other cultural products, including fiction. This edges towards what Jean Baudrillard has termed &amp;ldquo;theory fiction&amp;rdquo;&amp;ndash;theory that attempts to catch an ever-moving present by anticipating the future. As Douglas Kellner explains, &amp;ldquo;[Baudrillard’s] recurrent theme is the destruction and disappearance of the real…In a Nietzschean mode, he suggests that henceforth truth and reality are illusions, that illusions reign, and that therefore people should respect illusion and appearance and give up the illusory quest for truth and reality&amp;rdquo; (Kellner, Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy). Knowledge is not so much truth but something located in the process of weaving itself: the point is not that women and cybernetics are ‘woven’ but that she is weaving them. There’s a bit of sorcery to this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2-53&lt;/strong&gt;. While Plant discusses (weaves?) further on the issue of feedback, here she preempts her own discussion of women’s role in footnotes in her discussion of cybernetic systems. According to Plant, &amp;ldquo;[R]ather than a linear operation, in which information comes in, is processed and goes out without any return, the cybernetic system is a feedback loop, hooked up and responsive to its own environment&amp;rdquo; (Plant, p. 53). Women’s role as reproducers of knowledge (scribes, etc.) is not simply the reproduction of the same, but an active project of providing successive feedbacks on the information provided&amp;ndash;as with Ada Lovelace, in the form of footnotes. Footnotes, unlike the text itself, are far more likely to change and be modified over time. It is here that there is some power in being responsive to the new developments and sociopolitical circumstances of the day&amp;ndash;a power chiefly exercised by women situated in anonymous roles (what Plant calls &amp;ldquo;behind the veil&amp;rdquo;). Women’s personal non-identity is precisely her power: the reproduction of the same (of the dominant ideology, of maleness) is never quite so &lt;em&gt;same&lt;/em&gt;. Baudrillard’s project&amp;ndash;of catching the present and anticipating the future&amp;ndash;is primarily modified through these kind of cybernetic feedback loops. It is not about being &amp;ldquo;True&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;False&amp;rdquo; but being &lt;em&gt;responsive&lt;/em&gt; that counts, and this works two ways: responding and being responded to by text. Nonetheless, this literary feedback loop is rather limited&amp;ndash;chiefly limited to those woman who could, in fact, write. Plant’s piece lacks in its consideration of class and race, but the commitment to partiality leaves open alternative strategies for weaving beyond the written word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3-56&lt;/strong&gt;. Weaving, for Plant, is not just woman’s limit (or her role), but her strength and great, and very necessary, contribution. Plant finds change in the process itself: &amp;ldquo;[p]erhaps weaving is even the fabric of every other discovery and invention, perhaps the beginning and the end of their history&amp;rdquo; (Plant, p. 56).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4-60&lt;/strong&gt;. Here Plant claims that &amp;ldquo;Entering the matrix is no assertion of masculinity, but a loss of humanity; to jack into cyberspace is not to penetrate, but to be invaded&amp;rdquo;. The Matrix is, for Plant, built by weaving. There is something quite powerful in Plant’s work about the notion of a dispersive critique&amp;ndash;one that does not penetrate with a new arborescent centrality but instead liquifies itself and attaches itself to all sides and in every nook and cranny. May the footnote begin a kind of liquid intervention in a text?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5-63-64&lt;/strong&gt;. &amp;ldquo;[I]n translating Menabrea’s work from French, [Ada] provided footnotes more detailed and substantial&amp;ndash;three times as long, in fact&amp;ndash;than the text itself&amp;rdquo;. Alfred Whitehead once said that &amp;ldquo;The safest general characterization of the European philosophical tradition is that it consists of a series of footnotes to Plato&amp;rdquo; (Whitehead, Process and Reality, p. 39). Ada’s method&amp;ndash;like other women’s weaving practices&amp;ndash;takes this to an extreme, and Plant footnotes Ada’s work by taking this &amp;ldquo;marginal zone occupied by women writers, [those] who could write&amp;rdquo; and stripping it of everything disempowering: &amp;ldquo;never within the body of the text, women have nevertheless woven their influence between the lines&amp;rdquo; (Plant, p. 64). Footnote-weaving is not just a method, it is a &lt;em&gt;tactic&lt;/em&gt; that women employ not just out of necessity, nor just because weaving is &lt;em&gt;what women do&lt;/em&gt;, but as an alternative to patriarchal and authoritative approaches, avoiding many of the perennial pitfalls of feminists knowledge production: we do not have ‘one’ account, and certainly not an exhaustive account, only connections between accounts that are made, sometimes for the first time, to speak together. It straddles the line between between a lack of voice and a multiplicity of voices, indeed, weaving works as an operating system of knowledge production, taking the raw material of patriarchal knowledge and distorting it beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hyper-Stratification and Cybernetic Capital</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-04-20-hyper-stratification-and-cybernetic-capital/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-04-20-hyper-stratification-and-cybernetic-capital/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;dystopian-cyberspace&#34;&gt;Dystopian Cyberspace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an increasingly totalitarian streak in how we interface with technology, and with each other through technologically augmented cyber spatial forms of communication (AKA, social media). The 90s dream of limitless communication with infinitely diverse strangers has been all but squashed. Facebook, for example, made explicit changes to its algorithm last year to show you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.niemanlab.org/2018/03/has-facebooks-algorithm-change-hurt-hyperpartisan-sites-according-to-this-data-nope/&#34;&gt;more of the people you already know&lt;/a&gt;—essentially a curated list of the people you&amp;rsquo;re most willing to tolerate—in your news feeds, rather than public figures, communities, and online publications. In response to the harassment campaigns of the mid 2010s (e.g. #gamergate), Facebook and Twitter have both introduced a wide range of features to limit who you can see and who can see you (via muting, unfollowing, blocking, etc.). Most notably, Twitter allows for publicly shareable and importable block lists, whereby Twitter communities collectively block hundreds or thousands of accounts altogether, creating heavily curated walled cyber-gardens. Clearly, things haven&amp;rsquo;t quite worked out, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think many of us saw the situation getting as bad as it did through the course of the 2010s. And it&amp;rsquo;s probably not getting any better.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h2 id=&#34;dystopian-cyberspace&#34;&gt;Dystopian Cyberspace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s an increasingly totalitarian streak in how we interface with technology, and with each other through technologically augmented cyber spatial forms of communication (AKA, social media). The 90s dream of limitless communication with infinitely diverse strangers has been all but squashed. Facebook, for example, made explicit changes to its algorithm last year to show you &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.niemanlab.org/2018/03/has-facebooks-algorithm-change-hurt-hyperpartisan-sites-according-to-this-data-nope/&#34;&gt;more of the people you already know&lt;/a&gt;—essentially a curated list of the people you&amp;rsquo;re most willing to tolerate—in your news feeds, rather than public figures, communities, and online publications. In response to the harassment campaigns of the mid 2010s (e.g. #gamergate), Facebook and Twitter have both introduced a wide range of features to limit who you can see and who can see you (via muting, unfollowing, blocking, etc.). Most notably, Twitter allows for publicly shareable and importable block lists, whereby Twitter communities collectively block hundreds or thousands of accounts altogether, creating heavily curated walled cyber-gardens. Clearly, things haven&amp;rsquo;t quite worked out, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think many of us saw the situation getting as bad as it did through the course of the 2010s. And it&amp;rsquo;s probably not getting any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick Land famously (and rather racistly) detailed how emerging technologies &amp;ldquo;which will also be unevenly distributed by SES [socioeconomic status], will certainly intense the trend to [neo-]speciation&amp;rdquo;, giving birth to a &amp;ldquo;trans-racial, infra-racial, and hyper-racial&amp;rdquo; future that will leave &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;race politics&amp;rsquo; as a gibberish ruin in its wake&amp;rdquo;, tearing apart human populations on increasingly stratified lines. Land explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assortative mating tends to genetic diversification. This is neither the preserved diversity of ordinary racism, still less the idealized genetic pooling of the anti-racists, but a class-structured mechanism for population diremption, on a vector towards neo-speciation. It implies the disintegration of the human species, along largely unprecedented lines, with intrinsic hierarchical consequence. The genetically self-filtering elite is not merely different—and becoming ever more different—it is explicitly superior according to the established criteria that allocate social status (Land 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see this already in social media, where communities trends toward increasing insularity and stratification, on both identitarian and ideological lines. But while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=meatspace&#34;&gt;meatspace&lt;/a&gt; segregation may restrict one to single-identity states or communities, the new cybersocial stratification allows that and more: ideologically uniform cyberspaces. Though we would prefer our communities to be diverse on account of their geographic spread, and that on this account we are somehow exempt from emergent hyper-stratification, the new ideological unitarianism is nonetheless a new cultural speciation (this need not be biological or genetic) that greatly alters the type and quality of our interactions with difference. In this ideological neo-speciation, social relationships are reconfigured into misalignment with meatspace communities—cyberspace is a diaspora, after all—and these reconfigurations may be even more totalitarian than their meatspace predecessors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Queer cyberspace is a good example, particularly because the proliferation of any notion of the &amp;lsquo;queer&amp;rsquo; has occurred largely through social media, rather than through physical interaction. Virulent conflicts rage over proper language and abstract notions of &amp;ldquo;inclusion&amp;rdquo;—Who gets to call themselves &amp;lsquo;queer&amp;rsquo;? Is queer better than &amp;lsquo;gay&amp;rsquo; or &amp;rsquo;lesbian&amp;rsquo;?  Is x or y group being erased? The rhetoric here is quite extreme, and quickly becomes wrapped up in moralizing language about who or what is &amp;lsquo;hurting&amp;rsquo; the imagined community or who/what is &amp;lsquo;dangerous&amp;rsquo; to the ideological cause. This works in no particular direction: anti-queer LGBT cyberspace (i.e. people who reject queer politics and theory) is just as rabid as pro-queer LGBT cyberspace. That&amp;rsquo;s not the point, rather, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; important is that these communities are imagined in the most literal sense: they don&amp;rsquo;t exist in any given locale. They are purely ideological assemblages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location in cyberspace is not physical. Instead, it is ideological—it pulls together diverse and opposed groups because it is established through disposition, orientation, and relationship to others. Consider gaming communities, where previously geographic communities—loosely predicted based on culture, identity, or status—are replaced with massively online international cyberspaces, which are instead oriented toward ideological beliefs such as &amp;ldquo;Overwatch is a good game&amp;rdquo;, often devoid of any practical element (i.e. not just communities of Overwatch players, but communities interested in Overwatch that believe it to be a good game). The most bitter conflict of the 90s—Nintendo vs. Sega—had something to do with organizing around a common physical object (a console and its games). But nowadays, the biggest games are multi-platform, and gaming communities organize around connected bits of software (i.e. Overwatch, Fortnite, or some other game), rather than physical hardware. In cyberspace, locations are purely signifiers, and this tends to magnify ideological difference, bring together awkward bedfellows and tentative allies. For gamers, that means constructing community based on disposition (not just video games as a practice, but video games as a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo;), rather than some kind of meatspace commonality. And because these are primarily ideological communities, any critique of video games (as a whole or in the particular) is taken as particularly injurious. The Sony fans, the Xbox fans, and the PC fans all set aside their differences and relocate to a common orientational locale to &amp;ldquo;defend&amp;rdquo; the hobby from the injurious entity. As Nick Land points out, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;racists and anti-racists can be expected to eventually bond in a defensive fraternity, when they recognize that traditionally-differentiated human populations are being town asunder on an axis of variation that dwarfs all of their established concerns&amp;rdquo; (Land 2014).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cyberspace is a multiplicity of locales, meaning that every possible ideological permutation sparks new micro-communities, infinitely overlapping and violently opposed. Activist spaces are a particularly potent example because the stakes &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; so high, and terms like &amp;ldquo;the black community&amp;rdquo;, which once referred to geographically contingent communities, are now infinitely splintered and  ripped apart as new space is carved out online. More than ever, black women, for example, are spoken of in oppositional terms to black men, regardless of geographic proximity, they are discursively rendered &amp;ldquo;apart&amp;rdquo;. In crossover with trans communities, the need for specificity has manifested in long series of identifiers—it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;trans people&amp;rdquo; who are facing violence, it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;black trans women sex workers&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. Black trans women are then pried apart from the cisgender black community—it&amp;rsquo;s an infinite dialectic, and in the new cyber-homesteading, specificity is a virtue. The constant fracturing of new, overlapping subspaces in ever more oppositional terms is made possible precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; cyberspace is so limitless; we see nothing so extreme in meatspace, where creating microspaces is costly, difficult, or even impossible. Online, to be oppositional is to be informed, moral, even woke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-and-going-to-capital&#34;&gt;Coming and Going to Capital&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our connectedness to cyberspace grows, so do the swiftness and intensity of our efforts to defend our space from ideological transgressions, real or imagined. Being &amp;ldquo;connected&amp;rdquo; technologically (having technocapital and knowing how to use it) births social capital, and well-connected and Extremely Online People (TM) are able to exert a larger role in not only establishing cybersocial norms, but also meatspace norms that are increasingly subordinate to cyberspatial politics. And because technocapital and the knowledge to use it is distributed unevenly across the world and across socioeconomic status, the emergence of the cyperspatial primacy effectively cuts off most of the world from these processes, or segregates them into more local communities divided by language, time zone, etc. And within those segregations, they are further devolved into the same mesh of micro-cyberstates as the West, but these are even more hyper-local.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of punishment, two distinct forms arise: social and technological. In the former, which is not exclusive to cyberspace but greatly magnified by it, individuals are subject to brigading, denouncing, mobbing, etc. In the latter, individuals fall victim to banning, blocking, block lists, block chains, DDoSing, doxing, hacking, SWATing, etc. All of these require a certain connectedness to technocapital—access and knowledge of technology. Technological forms of  punishment result in complete social isolation/solitary confinement—a form of torture—or in terroristic assaults on life and property (DDoSing personal websites, hacking bank accounts, SWATing randos at 3AM, etc.). On Twitter, I&amp;rsquo;ve found the willingness to block quite extraordinary; a critical quote tweet here or a skeptical reply there means being blocked within seconds, often by complete strangers, regardless of the quality or intent of one&amp;rsquo;s criticism. It&amp;rsquo;s worse than automated. Unlike meatspace, where we cannot &amp;lsquo;ban&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;block&amp;rsquo; others for minor transgressions, banning and blocking becomes a second nature and thoughtless act. And while mobbing may be quite the physical exertion in meatspace, mobbing is effortless and inevitable in cyberspace. The technological intersects the social even more profoundly with Twitter&amp;rsquo;s shareable block lists (coupled with third-party tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://blocktogether.org&#34;&gt;Block Together&lt;/a&gt;), which allow hundreds of people to collectively isolate a particular user within minutes. While this happens informally in meatspace and elsewhere on cyberspace, on Twitter proficiency with advanced blocking tools plays a directly deterministic role in the kinds of people and ideologies we interact with. Naturally, social capital shapes which blocklists are followed—simultaneously deciding who is allocated social capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interplay between social and technological forms of punishment shows precisely how they congeal to form &lt;em&gt;technosocial&lt;/em&gt; capital, and in cyberspace technosocial capital (or cybernetic capital) emerges as technocapital augments and transforms existing social or symbolic capital—it&amp;rsquo;s the hyper-currency of our hyper-racist cyberspace. In &lt;em&gt;The Logic of Practice&lt;/em&gt;, French sociologist Pierre Bourdieu writes that &amp;ldquo;symbolic capital is credit&amp;hellip;a kind of advance, a credence, that only the group&amp;rsquo;s belief can grant those who give it the best symbolic and material guarantees&amp;hellip;symbolic capital is one of the mechanisms which make capital go to capital&amp;rdquo; (Bourdieu 1992, 120). While Bourdieu doesn&amp;rsquo;t address cyberspace (obviously), he does address at least one similar yet comparatively primitive technological innovation: literacy (and after all, are we all not &amp;ldquo;computer literate&amp;rdquo;?). Bourdieu argues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By detaching cultural resources from persons, literacy enables a society to move beyond anthropological limits particularly those of individual memory - and liberates it from the constraints implied mnemotechnic devices such as poetry, the conservation technique par excellence of non-literate societies; it makes it possible to accumulate the culture previously conserved in the incorporated state and, by the same token, to perform the primitive accumulation of cultural capital, the total or partial monopolizing of the society&amp;rsquo;s symbolic resources in religion, philosophy, art and science, through the monopolization of the instruments for appropriation of these resources (writing, reading and other decoding techniques), henceforward preserved not in memories but in texts (Bourdieu 1992, 125).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, new communicative computing technologies propel the circulation of cultural capital by a function of economic capital (access to technology) and non-computing technologies such as literacy. In the emergent hyper-capitalized (cyber)space, these kinds of capital, along with references to prior cybercultural events, are affectively what makes inclusion happen, by creating shared reservoirs of cultural knowledge and practice that are crucial to shaping highly stratified and totalitarian micro-states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this conversion is two-way, because techno social capital can be readily converted into economic capital. We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen it happen: someone with thousands of followers starts a GoFundMe or shares a Cash App link and it fills up within hours. Someone starts a YouTube channel. Someone gets a brand deal on Instagram and they&amp;rsquo;re rolling in the dough. We all know this would never happen if they had a few dozen followers. But nevertheless, this new hyper-stratification means even those with few followers may be surrounded by small groups of rabidly loyal and ideologically homogenous fans—ready to mob, defend, and donate. In cyberspace, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen a rapid proliferation and decentralization of social capital. It&amp;rsquo;s no longer just a have-some/lack-some game of elites vs. everyone else (or bourgeois vs. proletariat), it&amp;rsquo;s a game that everyone plays and from which we all benefit. We&amp;rsquo;re all implicated in this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;affective-impossibilities&#34;&gt;Affective Impossibilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think some may take issue with characterizing social media as &amp;rsquo;totalitarian&amp;rsquo;, and would probably disavow this game in its most abstract excesses. They&amp;rsquo;ll probably assert the right of communities to form these spaces, or that these communities actually return socio capital to the marginalized through some narrative of empowerment. They might also argue that the violence comes from the forces outside the community that demand entry. But technosocial violence arises precisely &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; violence is disavowed in key contexts. Bourdieu puts it well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So long as overt violence, that of the usurper or the ruthless master, is collectively disapproved of and is liable to provoke either a violent riposte or the flight of the victim - that is, in both cases, for lack of any legal recourse, the destruction of the very relationship that was to be exploited - symbolic violence, gentle, invisible violence, unrecognized as such, chosen as much as undergone, that of trust, obligation, personal loyalty, hospitality, gifts, debts, piety, in a word, of all the virtues honoured by the ethic of honour, presents itself as the most economical mode of domination because it best corresponds to the economy of the system (Bourdieu 1992, 127).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bourdieu&amp;rsquo;s point on invisible violence is reiterated by the late Mark Fisher in &lt;em&gt;Capitalist Realism&lt;/em&gt;. Building from Žižek, Fisher explains that &amp;ldquo;[c]apitalist ideology&amp;hellip;consists precisely in the overvaluing of belief—in the sense of inner subjective attitude—at the expense of the beliefs we exhibit and externalize in our behavior. So long as we believe (in our hearts) that capitalism is bad, we are free to continue to participate in capitalist exchange&amp;rdquo; (Fisher 2009, 26). Capital thus relies on a series of disavowals, and my point is that one need not explicitly hold the violent effects of technosocial capital as virtuous in order to participate in its exchange. And it&amp;rsquo;s not just capital that&amp;rsquo;s exchanged in these interactions, it&amp;rsquo;s also affect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exchanges of affect are instrumental in orienting individuals with space. Sara Ahmed suggests that emotions &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;create the very effect of the surfaces or boundaries of bodies and worlds&amp;rdquo;, and that emotions &amp;ldquo;do things, and they align individuals with communities&amp;mdash;or bodily space with social space&amp;mdash;through the very intensity of their attachments&amp;rdquo; (Ahmed 2004, 117-119). In cyberspace, communities (and bodies) are not so much separated by physical location anymore, but rather in their affective orientation towards the Other. Cohesive communities depend on a kind of affective cohesion, which is usually accomplished through fear and hate toward the Other—and as Ahmed notes, &amp;ldquo;hate is economic; it circulates between signifiers in relationships of difference and displacement&amp;rdquo; (Ahmed 2004, 119).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long ago, Anthropologist Mary Douglas noted that along lines of purity, &amp;ldquo;anomalous events may be labelled dangerous&amp;hellip;attributing danger is one way of putting a subject above dispute&amp;hellip;it also helps to enforce conformity&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; (Douglas 2013, 40-41). Ahmed&amp;rsquo;s work on racist hate is particularly applicable here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emotion of hate works to animate the ordinary subject, to bring that fantasy to life, precisely by constituting the ordinary as in crisis, and the ordinary person as the real victim. The ordinary becomes that which is already under threat by imagined others whose proximity becomes a crime against person as well as place. The ordinary or normative subject is reproduced as the injured party: the one &amp;ldquo;hurt&amp;rdquo; or even damaged by the &amp;ldquo;invasion&amp;rdquo; of others. The bodies of others are hence transformed into &amp;ldquo;the hated&amp;rdquo; through a discourse of pain. They are assumed to &amp;ldquo;cause&amp;rdquo; injury to the ordinary white subject, such that their proximity is read as the origin of bad feeling: indeed, the implication here is that the white subject&amp;rsquo;s good feelings (love, care, loyalty) are being &amp;ldquo;taken&amp;rdquo; away by the abuse of such feelings by others (Ahmed 2004, 118).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hate thus relies on a discourse of terrorism. Ahmed further suggests that &amp;ldquo;fear works to create a sense of being overwhelmed: rather than being contained in an object, fear is intensified by the impossibility of containment&amp;rdquo; (Ahmed 2004, 124). This sense provides the impetus for totalitarian excess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, many on the left would take issue with being compared to the white supremacists in Ahmed&amp;rsquo;s work, and many might argue that technosocial tools (banning, blocking, muting, etc.) were necessary innovations to better combat online harassment, especially in the post-GamerGate era, or that these tools are actually emancipatory because they make people in marginal positions safer, and that the persistence of harassment is reason enough for their existence. But as Mark Fisher points out, &amp;ldquo;[t]he role of capitalist ideology is not to make an explicit case for something in the way that propaganda does, but to conceal the fact that the operations of capital do not depend on any sort of subjectively assumed belief&amp;rdquo; (Fisher 2009, 25). Fisher explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all that we know, the authoritarian measures that are everywhere in place could have been implemented within a political structure that remains, notionally, democratic. The War on Terror has prepared us for such a development: the normalization of crisis produces a situation in which the repealing of measures brought in to deal with an emergency becomes unimaginable (when will the war be over?) (Fisher 2009, 10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unimaginability of &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; other than these totalitarian doctrines is closely related to Fisher&amp;rsquo;s capitalist realism—&amp;ldquo;the widespread sense that not only is capitalism the only viable political and economic system, but also that it is now impossible even to imagine a coherent alternative to it&amp;rdquo; (Fisher 2009, 10). The normalization of crisis is all too familiar in the post-GamerGate era, and leftists often stress the need to &amp;ldquo;protect themselves&amp;rdquo; or their communities from sexist or racist assault. But we&amp;rsquo;ve created the Patriot Act of cyberspace: totalitarianism in the name of liberty. Go Figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I am not arguing for a moral condemnation of anyone who&amp;rsquo;s ever blocked someone—or anyone who&amp;rsquo;s ever harassed someone, for that matter. I&amp;rsquo;m not particularly interested in moralism. But what I am suggesting is that the incentive structure in cyberspace is such that we cannot imagine a cyberspace free of capital and totalitarian border practices. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean cyberspace is all bad—clearly, it&amp;rsquo;s put people in contact that would have never met before. We don&amp;rsquo;t know how things will be, and there&amp;rsquo;s potential in that. But for now, this is the way things are: we&amp;rsquo;re in a feedback loop that stabilizes the cyber-structure, deepening its stratifying powers. The popular self-help gospel of the cyberage is to log off and disconnect, our phones and tablets already have utilities built-in to help us/force us to log off, as if going back to meatspace is supposed to be somehow more healthy. But is the solution really to try to go back to some primitive pre-internet state? Following Mark Fisher&amp;rsquo;s beautiful work on the same subject, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://markfisherreblog.tumblr.com/post/32522465887/terminator-vs-avatar-notes-on-accelerationism&#34; title=&#34;Terminator vs. Avatar: Notes on Accelerationism&#34;&gt;Terminator vs. Avatar: Notes on Accelerationism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced we can go back to a meatspace not implicated in cyberspace, or that it would even be desirable if we could. And, given that cyberspace is multiple, it offers a loosening of connections never possible in meatspace. In meatspace, if your identity-community decides to shut you out, there&amp;rsquo;s no exit. In cyberspace, you just go somewhere else, throw up a different pseudonym, and do your best to move on: there&amp;rsquo;s always an exit, and another opportunity. It may strike us as foreign, but is there really any other option? We&amp;rsquo;ve got to see this through: even if we become unrecognizable in the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ahmed, Sara. 2004. &amp;ldquo;Affective Economies.&amp;rdquo; Social Text 22 (2): 117–39. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-22-2_79-117&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-22-2_79-117&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Block Together.&amp;rdquo; n.d. Accessed April 20, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blocktogether.org/&#34;&gt;https://blocktogether.org/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bourdieu, Pierre. 1992. The Logic of Practice. Translated by Richard Nice. Stanford University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Douglas, Mary. 2013. Purity and Danger: An Analysis of Concepts of Pollution and Taboo. Hoboken : Taylor and Francis, 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fisher, Mark. 2009. Capitalist Realism: Is There No Alternative? Zero Books. Winchester: O Books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;———. 2010. &amp;ldquo;Terminator vs. Avatar: Notes on Accelerationism.&amp;rdquo; Mark Fisher ReBlog (blog). April 14, 2010. &lt;a href=&#34;http://markfisherreblog.tumblr.com/post/32522465887/terminator-vs-avatar-notes-on-accelerationism&#34;&gt;http://markfisherreblog.tumblr.com/post/32522465887/terminator-vs-avatar-notes-on-accelerationism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Land, Nick. 2014. &amp;ldquo;Hyper-Racism.&amp;rdquo; Outside In (blog). September 29, 2014. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.xenosystems.net/hyper-racism/&#34;&gt;http://www.xenosystems.net/hyper-racism/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owen, Laura. n.d. &amp;ldquo;Has Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm Change Hurt Hyperpartisan Sites? According to This Data, Nope.&amp;rdquo; Nieman Lab (blog). Accessed April 20, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.niemanlab.org/2018/03/has-facebooks-algorithm-change-hurt-hyperpartisan-sites-according-to-this-data-nope/&#34;&gt;https://www.niemanlab.org/2018/03/has-facebooks-algorithm-change-hurt-hyperpartisan-sites-according-to-this-data-nope/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Urban Dictionary: Meatspace.&amp;rdquo; n.d. Urban Dictionary. Accessed April 20, 2019. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=meatspace&#34;&gt;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=meatspace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
